Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Good
ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. We begin now the beginning of the seventh
פרק, perek, top of מ"ה עמוד א, mem-heh amud aleph, and let's
get started.
שלושה שאכלו כאחד חייבין לזמן. Shlosha she'achlu ke'achat chayavin lezamen. The last
פרק perek had all been about the opening ברכות, brachot, and this
פרק perek focuses on ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and particularly with a
זימון. zimun. It actually occurred to me last night after the שיעור,
shiur, I asked why the last פרק perek had right near the
end the issue about the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon on a fruit
and on רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's vegetables. And I think the reason
was because it probably even though it was this פרק perek is
really focused on זימון zimun and ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, but probably
because it wanted to wrap up all the distinctions between different types
of food stuffs, fruit, vegetables, and so on, whereas this פרק perek
really assumes we're talking about a bread meal and does not want
to get into distinctions between different types of foods and really just
focuses on the act of ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon as well. So
that might be why we have a little bit of that last
time to put the fruit issue aside. Anyway, this פרק perek begins
with ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and with the זימון. zimun. Now the
זימון zimun as we
know is you say רבותי נברך, rabotai nevarech, you call people to
bless, to join you together with
a blessing, and then ברוך שאכלנו משלו ובטובו חיינו, baruch she'achalnu mishelo
uv'tuvo chayinu, ברוך שאכלנו משלו, baruch she'achalnu mishelo, ברוך שאכלנו משלו ובטובו
חיינו, baruch she'achalnu mishelo uv'tuvo chayinu, let us bless the one from
whom we have eaten from, and it brings the group together and
say basically as a group let us bless and thank God. And
as I've mentioned to you before by the opening ברכה bracha and
here too also by the end ברכה bracha that when it comes
to ברכות הנהנין, brachot hanehenin, possibly also תפילה, tefilla, fundamentally you're not
supposed to do this שומע כעונה shomea ke'oneh by piggybacking on somebody
else. Fundamentally you are supposed to do it yourself, and the exception
however is when you are doing it as a corporate entity as
part of a group, not responding to another individual, but you are
seen as a group and one person is speaking for the group.
And this is the idea of זימון zimun by ברכת המזון. Birkat
Hamazon. Originally it was not just in order to say a few
extra lines before בענטשינג, bensching, but the real purpose was to create
everybody there as a group and do it as the ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon of the group. And that only the מזמן mezamen would
say it and everybody else would be יוצא. yotze. So that is
the classic זימון, zimun, not what we have where everybody does it
individually and you just say a few sentences in the beginning. It's
really that the מזמן mezamen says some opening words, everybody joins in,
and then through the מזמן mezamen's ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon everybody fulfills
their obligation. So let's take a look now at the opening משנה.
mishna.
Do I have a text for you?
Yeah, yeah, we'll see. שלושה שאכלו כאחד. Shlosha she'achlu ke'achat. שלושה שאכלו
כאחד, Shlosha she'achlu ke'achat, so three people ate together as a group,
חייבין לזמן, chayavin lezamen, they have to
לזמן, lezamen, meaning like call one another together, do the זימון, zimun,
invite, right. So, אכל דמאי. achal demai. Now, that's in the general
rule. Now we right away without even talking about what this זימון
zimun is or anything we jump right into some exceptions. אכל דמאי
ומעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו. achal demai uma'aser rishon she'nitla trumato. The basic
point of this משנה mishna is going to be that if the
food was eaten was some form of a forbidden food, then that
person does not become part of the זימון. zimun.
And not only because he's different from the other people, even if
everybody ate a forbidden food, there's a question if you're even supposed
to do a ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon if you've eaten forbidden food,
but certainly you're not supposed to do this זימון zimun which is
calling everybody to praise God here after this event of having eaten
these forbidden foods. So the משנה mishna's going to distinguish between foods
that are close to being forbidden and are but are okay and
foods that are really forbidden. So let's take a look. There's a
whole parallel list that's going to appear now in the משנה. mishna.
So if somebody ate דמאי, demai, דמאי demai is food as I
mentioned to you grain that was taken from the עמי הארץ, amei
ha'aretz, people that are just the masses not part of the rabbinic
class, generally assumed to be not so careful in taking תרומות ומעשרות.
trumot umasrot. The majority of them did but there was a significant
minority that did not and the rabbis insisted that if you buy
grain from them you have to take תרומות ומעשרות trumot umasrot again.
However, although it was forbidden rabbinically, it was not as forbidden as
other types of rabbinic food. So for example you could feed guests
דמאי demai because basically if you didn't have enough food for them
whatever, the rabbis let you feed the guests דמאי. demai. If you
were poor and sometimes you are allowed to eat דמאי, demai, so
it was not as across the board forbidden as other types of
things, even rabbinically forbidden things. One way in which this is sometimes
explained is that as opposed to saying something is rabbinically forbidden like
let's say I don't know chicken and milk, if you cook them
together that's only rabbinic, where there we basically say that becomes like
a טריף, treif, something
that's דרבנן derabbanan טריף treif but it's טריף. treif. דמאי demai is
less that the food is forbidden, it's more that you have an
obligation to take תרומות ומעשרות trumot umasrot before eating it, but it's
less that the food is forbidden as a food. forbidden food and
therefore under some circumstances people will be allowed to eat it and
that's also why if you ate it you're allowed to do a
זימון zimun because we don't treat it as forbidden food the same
way we do other things even other rabbinic foods. Yes?
Then doesn't that play well with the price and basically keeps the
rabbinic classes, whatever they are, on people would prefer buying their produce
because if you buy from non-rabbinic class then you're going to have
to take part of that and so,
so people would rather, so it's basically keeping, protecting the rabbinic classes
in business
and making everyone else's produce less value.
Right. I never thought about that.
And therefore the prices are going to be lower because, yeah
I hear the point, I hear the point. I never thought about
that. I don't know how many, I had somehow always assumed that
almost all the produce was דמאי. demai. I mean I, you know,
I don't know how many of the rabbis were involved in farming
and whatever. That was sort of my assumption that it's a very
tiny, thank you, percentage of the market that you can, that you
know, that sort of like you know is not a concern. I
think the analog nowadays would be like stuff that has a הכשר
hechsher and stuff that doesn't have a הכשר, hechsher, you know, that
type of stuff.
But you pay more for
stuff that has a הכשר. hechsher. Oh that's true, it's like the
reverse.
Yeah, in America everything has a
הכשר.
hechsher.
Right, but I hear the point. But wait a minute, could you
say the opposite? That it's the stuff that's cheaper that more people
would buy from it and you know and those that cared would
take the sacrifices and those that didn't would
not. Okay, it's an interesting question. I'd never thought about that, the
economic implications about דמאי. demai. It's a very good point.
It's a good point, meaning I again you have
to, right, I don't know enough about what percentage was and what
wasn't. I had always assumed that the vast majority was דמאי, demai,
but maybe you're right. But you know also there's an interesting question
about what is the side effect, what is the motivation you know
behind these types of things. I hear the point you're making. Again,
I don't know if I would think that that would be what
was motivating it. It might have been a side effect but, you
know, but yeah I hear the point.
Yes. So we're saying that this person ate the דמאי demai before
anybody separated it?
It became חסין chassin בוכא? bucha?
Okay, let's take a look. Okay, so that,
so, alright, so somebody eats דמאי demai ומעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו u'ma'aser
rishon she'nitlah trumato or the first מעשר ma'aser that the תרומה truma
was taken, after the לוי Levi gets מעשר ma'aser he takes תרומה
truma from it, a tenth of a tenth that goes to the
כהן Kohen and the rest is owned by the לוי Levi but
it's totally חולין, chullin, so anybody can eat from it, so you
know obviously that's okay. Although the
גמרא, Gemara, alright, the גמרא Gemara will try to explain what the
חידוש chiddush of this is. The פשט pshat of the משנה mishna
is there's no חידוש, chiddush, it's just to contrast it to the
next list, but the גמרא Gemara will explain why some of this
had to be said. מעשר שני והקדש שנפדו ma'aser sheni ve'hekdesh she'nifdu
or מעשר שני ma'aser sheni right which is taken every third and
sixth year, the second מעשר. ma'aser. Oh I'm sorry, which is taken
yeah which is taken every first, second, fourth and fifth year, excuse
me, which was the second מעשר ma'aser on the third and sixth
year it's מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Anyway, מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that
was redeemed, you're supposed to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim but instead
you're allowed to redeem it on coins and bring the coins to
ירושלים Yerushalayim or הקדש hekdesh or sanctified foods that were redeemed. All
of those things once they're redeemed they're חולין chullin so you're allowed
to eat them. והשמש ve'ha'shamash so all those are things which were
at one stage forbidden or quasi-forbidden but they become permissible and therefore
it's not a problem, which is relatively obvious. The last case however
is of a different type. והשמש שאכל כזית, ve'ha'shamash she'achal kezayit,
the attendant of the meal that eats a כזית. kezayit. Now there,
he's attending you at the meal, maybe he's given the right to
eat to snack a little bit as he's feeding you the food
and so on, but the question is, is he really part of
your group? You're not sitting here, you're not invited, you're not part
of the group, you're just the servant, you're just the guy serving,
you know, the waiter. So the חידוש chiddush here is that even
though he is really serving just as the waiter he is considered
to have eaten with the group and can be part of the
זימון. zimun. Okay so that is a different point than the earlier
ones. Yes?
From imported, from imported fruit you have to, you have to also
give
מעשר?
ma'aser? If you import from Israel, yes.
If you bring to Israel from another country?
No. If you import to Israel you do not give מעשר, ma'aser,
only stuff that's grown in Israel. Okay.
Now so והכותי, ve'ha'Kuti, the Samaritan, as we know sometimes Samaritans had
a debate whether they were considered Jews or not, so this משנה
mishna says yes, he is a Jew, all these מזמנין עליו mezamnin
alav they can be part of the זימון zimun of a group.
Now in the contrasting cases, אכל טבל, achal tevel, it's not just
דמאי demai where you don't know, it's real טבל, tevel, food that
really you know was not taken תרומות ומעשרות, trumot u'ma'asrot, biblically forbidden.
ומעשר ראשון שלא נטלה תרומתו u'ma'aser rishon she'lo nitlah trumato or the
first מעשר ma'aser that the תרומה truma was not taken, so then
it's really forbidden, it has תרומה truma mixed in, it can only
be eaten by a כהן. Kohen. ומעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו u'ma'aser
sheni ve'hekdesh she'lo nifdu and the second מעשר ma'aser and הקדש hekdesh
that were not redeemed, so they have to be eaten in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, forbidden to be eaten outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. והשמש שאכל פחות
מכזית ve'ha'shamash she'achal pachot mi'kezayit or the attendant who ate less than
a כזית kezayit which
really... והנכרי vehanochri or a non-Jew. So you see this second list
directly parallels the first list. All of these cases אין מזמנין עליו,
ein mezaminin alav, they cannot be part of the זימון zimmun either
because what they ate was forbidden or because they're not Jewish or
because they're not part of the group or they didn't eat enough.
Now נשים ועבדים וקטנים, nashim va'avadim u'ktanim, now we get to a
part that has been the subject of a lot of interesting discussion:
women, slaves, and children, אין מזמנין עליהם, ein mezaminin aleihem, they can
also be, you, meaning the men is the implicit audience, cannot be
have a זימון zimmun with them. The גמרא Gemara discusses them having
a זימון zimmun with themselves by themselves and also discusses what the
reasons of them are of that is, and that's another הלכה, halacha,
and we will, we will get to discuss that even today. So
hold on for that. עד כמה מזמנין, ad kama mezaminin, until what
is the minimum amount that you can do זימון? zimmun? So עד
כזית, ad kezayis, even if you eat as little as a כזית.
kezayis. Meaning for somehow which a lot, we're going down, normally we
expect to go up, how much you'd have to eat, a כזית.
kezayis. But here it's like, until how little is it still considered
that you can do זימון? zimmun? עד כזית. ad kezayis. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, עד כביצה, ad kebeitzah, it has to be
a כביצה kebeitzah because that is considered a significant amount in order
to, you know, be closer to the idea of satiating. It's interesting
that it raises this question from the perspective of זימון zimmun and
not the perspective of ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. So again, all of
this we will, we will discuss. First Charlie and then David.
Steinsaltz changed it to הגוי. hagoy.
הגוי. hagoy. That is interesting because נכרי nochri normally the, normally the
censoring is goes from גוי goy or נכרי nochri to עכו"ם. akum.
I've never seen נכרי nochri as a, as a, as like, as
a self-censored, you know, very often the word for non-Jew is self-censored
because they didn't want, you know, the Christians, the church to think,
to get upset and think it was referring to them, so they
changed it to עכו"ם, akum, "no, it's star worshippers, it's not you
guys" and so on, either changed it yourself then have the church
change it or burn it or whatever. But I never, but that
question about גוי, goy, נכרי nochri being preferred to גוי. goy. Yeah,
right here. All right, maybe, maybe it is. Maybe it's a different
גרסא, girsa, I don't know, I'd have to, I'd have to check.
No, instead of...
What does ArtScroll have? Because ArtScroll has also been pretty good, נכרי.
nochri. ArtScroll is pretty good also at getting back to the original
text, not for רש"י. Rashi. Sometimes they had a very funny omission,
mistake, omission for רש"י Rashi once before. That רש"י Rashi said, if
you remember, the גמרא Gemara earlier said about that the מינים minim
would think that there is only the, you didn't want to say
the עשרת הדברות aseret hadibros during דאוונינג davening because the מינים minim
would say there's no תורה Torah except the עשרת הדברות. aseret hadibros.
So the original גרסא girsa for רש"י Rashi said who are the
מינים? minim? תלמידי ישו. talmidei Yeshu. And the ArtScroll kept the original
version of רש"י Rashi which was עכו"ם. akum. So anyway, but okay,
but no, the ArtScroll is actually pretty good also in terms of
the גמרא Gemara text itself, getting back to the original text. Yes,
David?
Why do we have a different formulation here of what constitutes a
group of people eating together than we had before for making ברכות?
brachos? Meaning before it spoke about הסבה haseiba and here it speaks
about number of people? So that's a good question. So we'll talk
about the issue about is there a minimum number? It might be
that here for ברכת המזון birchas hamazon it's you need more people,
you need three and so on. Now you're saying besides the issue
of the number, like the question of like what types of foodstuff
you're eating...
now if you have three people eating and they're not talking to
each other, they're not in common... Right.
One minute, one minute, let David finish.
Yes, so... you mean here, oh, here it doesn't mention the requirement
of הסבה, haseiba, before it mentioned the requirement of הסבה. haseiba. That's
your point? Meaning there are two differences: by ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona
it mentioned הסבה haseiba and it didn't mention number, here it mentions
number without הסבה. haseiba. But דאכלו כאחת d'achlu k'achas seems to be
the point that they're eating as a group. We will discuss some
of that question about how to define grouping, but it is true,
it does not insist on the הסבה. haseiba.
My question is why they're using a different legal formulation.
Right, that's a good question. It could be, I don't know, it
could be, you know, that some of these, the whole sort of...
it's a question also like maybe these פרטים pratim were formulated more
as independent units. You almost get, you know, a sense that the
whole sort of style is a little bit different here. So I'll
have to think about that more. I will say in terms of
the issue about הסבה, haseiba, but think of you, rather than sort
of the literary answer, but the הלכה halacha point, when the גמרא
Gemara mentioned הסבה haseiba before, I see you, Charlie, when the Gemara
mentioned הסבה haseiba before by the ברכה ראשונה, bracha rishona, it quoted
ברייתות beraitos that also mentioned הסבה haseiba for ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon.
So there implicitly it extended it in other ברייתות beraitos to ברכת
המזון. birchas hamazon. Why you need three here and you didn't need
it before, we'll see in a minute in the גמרא Gemara that
there's a particular issue of three that's demanded more for ברכת המזון
birchas hamazon than by ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. But in terms of
like stylistically the difference, I'm not so sure. Yes?
Just to further confuse, the old Hebrew Steinsaltz kept נכרי, nochri, it's
only in the Koren that it got הגוי.
hagoy. Okay, so I don't know, I'd have to check the manuscript.
Now I do want to say before we get to... so David
raises good questions about הסבה haseiba and three, so to remind us,
the earlier גמרות gemaros did extend, ברייתות beraitos extended הסבה haseiba to
ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. Why you need three, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי, mena hanei milei, where does
this come from, this idea of three people joining together in
ברכת המזון? birchas hamazon? אמר רב אסי דאמר קרא, amar Rav Assi
d'amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, גדלו לה' אתי ונרוממה שמו יחדיו.
gadlu lashem iti u'neromema shemo yachdav. And then ונרוממה שמו יחדיו, unromemah
shemo yachdav, we'll do it together. So first you say, you know,
רבותי נברך, rabbotai nevarech, you know, ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד.
baruch shem kevod malchuto l'olam va'ed. So you know, you're calling on
them to bless, they say they bless God's name, right? That's, that's
גדלו. gadlu. And then ונרוממה שמו יחדיו, unromemah shemo yachdav, you know,
נברך לאלהינו? nevarech leloheinu? No, נברך שאכלנו משלו, nevarech sheachallnu mishelo, נברך,
nevarech,
let's all do it together as a group. So what?
That's for eating?
All right, so that's a good question. Let's see a little bit
more. But anyway, the text is basically calling to others, others responding
praising God, and then after you've called them and they respond, then
you're all together as a group, נברך. nevarech. So it's the יחדיו.
yachdav. רבי אבהו אמר מהכא, Rabbi Abbahu amar mehacha, from here. כי
שם ה' אקרא, ki shem Hashem ekra, when I call out the
name of God, הבו גודל לאלהינו, havu godel leloheinu, you give greatness
or, you know, elevation to our God. So that is the same
idea. I call out the name, you respond. The difference is is
that, you know, what's I think nicer in the first פסוק, posuk,
although this is from the תורה, Torah, is is that it has
the יחדיו yachdav element. That in the end we're somehow doing it
all together. It's not just a type of a responsive thing. I
say something and you respond and you praise God's name. Now Michael
asks of course a good question which is there's nothing here that
connects this to בנצ'ן. bentching.
You know, it is בנצ'ן bentching is the, is the one place
in the תורה Torah where it says that you have a מצוה
לברך, mitzvah levarech, ואכלת ושבעת וברכת. v'achalta v'savata uverachta.
So the other גמרא, Gemara, you know, but it is exactly, you
know, not clear, and there are other גמרות Gemaras that don't limit
this concept specifically, you know, to the idea of בנצ'ן. bentching. So
the גמרא Gemara really, it's true, it's not proving that it's a
biblical concept to do זימון. zimmun. But how do you know, where's
this institution of זימון zimmun indicated? And we do see the תורה
Torah has this idea of calling to others, others responding, doing it
together, praising God as a group, and especially as I said since
the idea of זימון zimmun here is not just the opening פסוקים,
psukim, but the opening, you know,
declarations, but doing the ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon as a group, you
know that after that calling and response you're now doing it together
as a group, the ונרוממה שמו יחדיו unromemah shemo yachdav is very,
you know, very much speaks to that. Again, not proving that it's
done at בנצ'ן, bentching, but it's an אסמכתא asmachta and it proves,
it proves the institution, the idea of this as an institution. Yeah.
When do you think public prayer begins?
Yeah,
I have no idea. What I could say is that I think
according to scholars the בית כנסת, Beis Knesset, the earliest uses of
the בית כנסת Beis Knesset was more for
קריאת התורה Krias HaTorah than it was for תפילה. tefillah. But you
know, the idea of תפילה, tefillah, for example, you know, many believe
that תהילים Tehillim was essentially the earliest prayer book and it was
written maybe as a way of saying either if you're not bringing
קרבנות korbanos or together with your קרבנות. korbanos. But when it sort
of, when the idea of doing it as a מנין minyan and
as a ציבור, tzibur, yeah, I'm sure there's some scholars who have
an opinion but I don't know it offhand.
Rabbi Abbahu is not suggesting that the זימון zimmun is דאורייתא de'oraisa
by bringing a פסוק posuk from the תורה? Torah?
You know, that's, that's what I, you know,
my response to Michael, you know, I'm basically assuming not that these
פסוקים psukim are more indicating... I'd have to see if there are
any... the general, you know, the general assumption is that it is
not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. I would not be surprised, and I'd have to
double check if there are ראשונים Rishonim who say that it is,
because the גמרא Gemara just throws quotes a straight פסוק. posuk. But
I think more, right, so I'd have to see if there are,
I would not be surprised if there are ראשונים Rishonim that say
it is.
But again, my sense more here is that it's being quoted to
show that maybe there's this institution of responding and doing it together,
but not necessarily that it's an obligatory thing to be done in
ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon דאורייתא. de'oraisa. What we can see is the
nature of this as a type of an institution. But I could
check, I'm sure there are ראשונים Rishonim who say yes. Okay, so
that's the idea of doing it with three, and that's by the
way why now the question that, you know, David raises about why
not in the beginning by the ברכה bracha at the beginning, why
doesn't it require three? You know, could you have the same idea
of כי שם ה' ki shem Hashem and so on? I don't
know the answer, I mean כי שם ה' ki shem Hashem definitely
is what leads you to the three, but notice when, you know,
the idea of הסבה haseiva in addition to not... the ברכה ראשונה
bracha rishona that we learned earlier, in addition to not requiring three,
it also doesn't have a text of זימון, zimmun, right? That's just
we're all reclining together and somehow joined to say the ברכה, bracha,
המוציא לחם מן הארץ Hamotzi Lechem Min Ha'aretz like we do as
a meal, right you don't say a זימון zimmun before you do
the three. So, it's not exactly clear why.
One explanation is, I'm trying to remember I think תוספות Tosafot says,
an interesting thing from, trying to remember from the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, let
me see if I can find it, that basically when you're coming
together for a meal, you're in the process of coming and you're
going to be staying some time together. So you need less to
form them as a group, whereas when you're ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon
everybody's getting ready to leave. So therefore you need something more to,
like, hold them together. You could have made the opposite argument. You
could have said that if you've been sitting together as a meal
you've already defined yourself as a group and you need less to
hold them together. So let me just see quickly and just try
to find the תוספות Tosafot that discusses this, one minute.
Take a look at אם רצו לזמן מזמנין Im ratzu lezamen mezamnin
תוספות. Tosafot. He says,
פירש רש"י וכן הן המוציא ושאר ברכות Perush Rashi ve-khen hen ha-motzi
u-she'ar berakhot אין אחד מברך להוציא חברו. ein echad mevarech le-hotzi chavero.
Okay, and then he quotes the earlier גמרא Gemara etc. So that's
the basic idea that for any ברכת הנהנין birkat ha-nehenin you're not
supposed to piggyback on somebody else, you need הסיבה. hisayva. And then
he says, one minute hold on, and then תוספות Tosafot says it's
not true, earlier the גמרא Gemara says that you can actually have
two people.
על כן נראה לי, Al ken ne-re li, this is like three
lines from the
bottom of this תוספות, Tosafot, דבברכה ראשונה מוציאין זה את זה שנים
וכולי. de-birka rishona motzi'in zeh et zeh shnayim ve-khulei. You don't need
three, two is good enough. דטעמא משום דהיינו לאכול יחד דעתן לצרף,
De-tama mishum de-haynu le-echol yachad daiten litzaref, אחד מברך להוציא חברו. echad
mevarech le-hotzi chavero. Because you're coming together, you're coming together in the
process of coming together, you don't need something special. אבל בברכה של
סוף סעודה שמסתלקת זה מזה צריך לברך כל אחד לעצמו. Aval be-vircha
shel sof se'udah she-mistaleket zeh mi-zeh tzarich levarech kol echad le-atzmo. But
if you're leaving one another, then without three and without the calling
to זימון, zimmun, it's somehow less of a group. Again, you could've
argued the opposite, that it's more of a group when you've been
sitting together than when you're just initially coming together. But there is
this thing question about מוציא motzi somebody else. תוספות Tosafot here does
not mention the earlier גמרא Gemara about the need of הסיבה. hisayva.
We had discussed that earlier, that even for the first ברכה beracha
you need הסיבה. hisayva. But even if you need some type of
הסיבה, hisayva, generally you should not make ברכות הנהנין birkat ha-nehenin for
somebody else. The demand is not as great as ברכת המזון. Birkat
HaMazon. The other possibility is simply that clearly ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon
has a lot more weight and a lot more status. It has
three ברכות, berachot, it's in the תורה. Torah. So it's a much
more sense of the הבו לה' אתי havu la-Shem iti and because
of the greater weight and the status of it, we demand it
more in order to do it as a group. We didn't treat
it as just any other ברכה beracha and therefore that's why we
demanded the זימון zimmun and that's why we demanded that you wanted
to give it that greater weight. Good question.
So let me if I'm understanding this correctly. So according to רש"י
Rashi then when we sit down, you know, שבת Shabbat meal, we
make המוציא, ha-motzi, I shouldn't be making המוציא ha-motzi for everybody else
unless there's three?
רש"י Rashi seems to say, at least what תוספות Tosafot quotes רש"י,
Rashi, that you need three. No, there is the idea of הסיבה
hisayva before. Don't worry so. But רש"י Rashi here, the way תוספות
Tosafot understood him, requires also that there be three. Okay. תוספות, Tosafot,
he, this simple reading of this תוספות Tosafot seems to go to
the opposite extreme. Not only do you not need three, you don't
even need הסיבה. hisayva. I don't know what he does with the
earlier גמרות. Gemaras. Okay, the simple sense of the earlier גמרא Gemara
is you need הסיבה hisayva but you don't need three, you don't
need a זימון, zimmun, you just can to say המוציא, ha-motzi, you
just for somebody else, you just need to be הסיבה. hisayva. תוספות
Tosafot even there said we don't really have הסיבה hisayva nowadays. But
any type of eating of bread, that's enough that you're together and
you can make. But other ברכות הנהנין birkat ha-nehenin you should not.
Okay, but there you don't need three. There you need three and
you need the פסוקים psukim of the זימון. zimmun.
In terms of what, being מוציא motzi somebody other ברכות הנהנין? birkat
ha-nehenin? Well, we'll see in the minute you בדיעבד bediavad you can
do this, but לכתחילה lechatchila you're not supposed to.
And במוציא b'motzi we said there's no problem even with less than
three.
Right, right, right. Okay, so anyway, so that, so that is an
interesting contrast of those two cases. Now, before we get on, I
want to make one other point related to the משנה mishna which
is very interesting and relevant point. That תוספות Tosafot has a discussion.
First, he thinks the reason you can't do a זימון zimmun with
somebody who ate non-כשר kosher food is since you're not allowed to
eat from his food, maybe you're not seen as a group. Then
תוספות Tosafot says it has nothing to do with being a group.
Somebody who eats non-כשר kosher food is fundamentally excluded from the זימון,
zimmun, there's even a question if he does a ברכת המזון Birkat
HaMazon and so on. But it does lead him to a question
about can you make a זימון zimmun with somebody who's eating food
that I can't eat? And what's an example? So he gives an
example about a כהן Kohen eating תרומה. terumah. Okay, can I make
a זימון zimmun with a כהן Kohen eating תרומה? terumah? I'm not
a כהן, Kohen, I can't be eating with him. And he quotes
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says yes you can because even though I can't
eat the כהן Kohen's food, the כהן Kohen can eat my food.
Okay, and then that leads תוספות Tosafot to a question about other
types of scenarios. Let's say, one minute, let's, we'll get there. Let's
say I have taken a נדר neder and I can't derive benefit
from you but you can derive benefit from me. So also we
can be a זימון zimmun because although I can't eat from you,
your food, you can eat from my food. If however we've taken
a vow that we can't derive benefit from one another, then we
are, then we cannot make a זימון. zimmun. So this leads to
the הלכה halacha about what if people are eating together, two people
are eating meat and one person is eating milk or vice versa?
Okay, or תוספות Tosafot gives an example that one person is careful
about פת עכו"ם pas akum and the others are not. So I
won't eat from your bread because you brought in, bakery, you know,
you brought supermarket bread and I only eat bread that's baked by
Jews. Okay, so I have certain חומרות, humros, I won't eat from
you but you're prepared to eat from me. Or מילכיגס milchigs and
פליישיגס. fleishigs. So again תוספות Tosafot says as long as some, as
you can eat from the other person's, you're okay. So if you'll
eat from his bread even if he won't eat from yours you're
okay. And in the מילכיגס milchigs פליישיגס fleishigs which תוספות Tosafot does
not discuss but later פוסקים poskim do, they say look, the guy
eating מילכיגס milchigs can wash out his mouth and eat פליישיגס. fleishigs.
Okay, you don't have to wait. So the guy פליישיגס fleishigs cannot
eat מילכיגס milchigs right now but the מילכיגס milchigs guy can eat
the פליישיגס. fleishigs. So then the whole question is who does the
זימון? zimmun? It's generally assumed the preference is that the זימון zimmun
is the guy eating מילכיגס milchigs because he at least is able
to have you know eaten from all the food whereas the guy
eating פליישיגס fleishigs is somewhat less the leader because you know more,
more they, that person cannot eat with the other. Very interesting question.
But an interesting question is about let's say the reason you can't
eat has to do more with like medical issues than הלכה *halachic*
issues. Right? Right. Exactly. Celiac and so on or just in general,
you know. Now by the way I should mention that the מילכיגס
*Milchigs* and פליישיגס *Fleishigs* is in itself less interesting. There was another
way to answer that, which was it really doesn't matter what you're
eating that's not the bread part. The זימון zimmun *zimun* is only
about the bread and therefore we could have eaten each other's bread,
we just couldn't eat each other's side dishes like the meat. So
anyway that's another interesting question. Do you focus on the bread here
or on the other parts of the meal? But for health issues,
I remember once looking it up. I don't think there's a lot
of literature on that but I think that mostly the פוסקים *poskim*
say that it's only if like it's a הלכה *halachic* barrier that
could create problems. If it's a health barrier we don't see that.
But you could say it not that way.
Like the זימון zimmun *zimun* because I have that all the time
because I'm celiac. I have a
מזומנת *mezumanet*. I always feel I can't lead
because you couldn't eat from their bread.
I can't eat bread at all.
Well that's a different... Oh you don't even eat there's no like
spelt or something. No. No. Aha. Aha. So that's a different issue.
That's somebody who's when two people ate bread and one person did
not. Okay? Right. So that will get there... No right. Lead. No.
Yes, participate but not lead. Yes. Yes. And we'll discuss that later.
But that's when one person isn't even eating bread. Yes.
Oh what if the bread is Wonder
Bread?
Wonder Bread is dairy. Oh so
that's a separate issue about dairy bread. Okay. Anyway but that's a
relevant הלכה *halacha* and also again if health issues are the reason
and that's interesting does that create a barrier as well. Yes.
Supermarket bread is not baked by a נחתום *nachthom*, it's פת עכו"ם
*pas akum*.
Well no when we say people are מחמיר *machmir* פת עכו"ם *pas
akum* it means even נחתום *nachthom*. If it's not פת עכו"ם *pas
akum* meaning that's the whole issue when it's not נחתום *nachthom* then
everybody says it's a problem. When it is you know פת פלטר
*pas palter*, right? That's where there's a חומרה *chumra* but right exactly.
Okay actually it's interesting because דווקא *davka* during the עשרת ימי תשובה
*Aseres Yemei Teshuva* where normally they say you should try to adopt
a little bit of some חומרה *chumra* in some area during עשרת
ימי תשובה *Aseres Yemei Teshuva*, there's a very long מנהג minhag *minhag*
in אשכנז *Ashkenaz* going back to the Middle Ages to be מחמיר
*machmir* in פת פלטר *pas palter*, bakery supermarket bread essentially during the
עשרת ימי תשובה *Aseres Yemei Teshuva*. So alright there's an interesting article
written on why that came up דווקא *davka* that חומרה *chumra*. Alright
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר רב Rav חנא בר אבא
*Amar Rav Chana bar Abba* said אמר רב Rav חנא בר אבא
*Rav Chana bar Abba*, מנין minyan לעונה אמן amein, שלא יהא קולו
יותר מן המברך *Minayin l'oneh amein shelo yehei kolo yoter min hamivarech*?
How do you know the person who says אמן *amein* should not
raise his voice higher than the one making the blessing? This could
be a good sermon also I'm sure as a metaphor. שנאמר *Shene'emar*,
גדלו לה' אתי ונרוממה שמו יחדיו yachdav, *Gadlu l'Hashem iti uneromemah shemo
yachdav*. Praise God with me
and we'll elevate His name together. So we're together, right? You don't
be louder than me. אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי *Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Pazi* said אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי *Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi*,
מנין minyan שאין המתרגם רשאי להגביה קולו יותר מן הקורא *Minayin she'ein
hamitargem rishai l'hagbi'ah kolo yoter min hakorei*? How do you know that
the מתרגם metargem? *mitargem*, they would have a מתרגם metargem *mitargem* during
the קריאת התורה *Krias HaTorah*, could not raise his voice louder than
the actual original text, the person reading the תורה *Torah* itself? שנאמר
*Shene'emar*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says, משה ידבר והאלקים יעננו בקול *Moshe
yedabeir v'ha'elokim ya'anenu b'kol*.
Moshe would speak and
God would respond to him in a voice. שאין תלמוד לומר בקול
*She'ein talmud lomar b'kol*, what does it mean in a voice? ומה
תלמוד לומר בקול *U'mah talmud lomar b'kol*? What does it mean a
voice? בקולו של משה *B'kolo shel Moshe*. In Moshe's voice meaning not
louder than Moshe. Now that's very bizarre because it makes it sound
like Moshe was reading the primary text and God was the מתרגם
*mitargem* and God wasn't louder than Moshe's voice. So first of all
I mean that's very strange. Also but the פסוק *pasuk* itself is
very strange. Moshe spoke and God responded to him? What does... I
mean it's a very hard פסוק *pasuk*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says
without explaining exactly the פסוק *pasuk*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says no, Moshe
had to speak loudly so everybody could hear him. Since God after
the first two דברות *dibros* was speaking only to Moshe, God didn't
have to speak loudly. So God really could have spoken at a
softer voice and then Moshe had to speak loudly so it could
be heard. But then the מתרגם *mitargem* would have been louder than
the קורא kore *korei*. So therefore God had to raise His voice
so that it was equivalent how תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* reads it, equivalent
to Moshe's voice so that the voice of the מתרגם *mitargem* was
not louder than the voice of the קורא kore *korei*. Again I
don't exactly get how to read the פסוק *pasuk* that Moshe speaks,
Moshe spoke after God respond... I you know it's a hard פסוק
*pasuk* in terms of that. Anyway we're not going to figure that
out now. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi* we taught similarly, אין
המתרגם רשאי להגביה קולו יותר מן הקורא *Ein hamitargem rishai l'hagbi'ah kolo
yoter min hakorei*. The מתרגם *mitargem* cannot lift his voice greater than
the one reading. ואם אי אפשר למתרגם להגביה קולו כנגד הקורא *V'im
ee efshar l'mitargem l'hagbi'ah kolo keneged hakorei*. Now we see the opposite.
Let's say he cannot lift his voice to be as loud as
the קורא *korei*. ימעך הקורא קולו ויקרא *Yama'eich hakorei kolo v'yikra*. That
there should be the similar same voice. The בעל קורא *baal korei*
should lower his voice so that the מתרגם *mitargem* is of equal.
Which is quite fascinating you know why is that. The מתרגם *mitargem*
is a translation. So what would be so bad if the translation
was a little bit lower, right, than it? I mean it's probably
that people can't hear but you're not raising the volume of the
מתרגם *mitargem* you're lowering the volume of the קורא *korei*. So it's
quite fascinating anyway. so people wouldn't devalue the תרגום, targum, you know,
תרגום, targum maybe it's so that they would be as attentive to
the תרגום targum, because most people probably couldn't understand the Hebrew, so
you didn't want to undermine the value of the תרגום, but it's
quite fascinating that it's just on the side, you know, until now
it seems like the original can be very loud, the response can't
be louder, and here you get this idea that they're both supposed
to be equal.
Is it possible that the consideration is more
for the emphasis on the קורא that
that it has to be at least as loud as the מתרגם?
I understand, but that's not what the last text said. Last text
said that they should be equal. Goes back to the יחדיו, yachdav
right? It's very nice to be doing it all יחדיו and doing
it together, but that might be מברך mevarech and עונה אמן. oneh
amen. Why that you have that idea, you know, that the, that
the, that even by the קורא and the מתרגם is an interesting
question. Yes. So all right, we'll keep on going. איתמר. itmar. Now,
so that's the idea of at least this opening, but ultimately again
it's important to keep in mind that the זימון zimmun. is not
just for a few lines in the beginning. Originally the function was
to bring them together as a group where one person is בענטשינג
bentshing for all of them. איתמר itmar was taught, שנים שאכלו כאחת,
shnayim she-achlu ke-achat, two people ate together. Again you have a זימון
zimmun? of two. שלשה shlosha has to make a זימון. zimmun. Is
two an optional זימון? zimmun So פליגי רב ורבי יוחנן, pligi Rav
ve-Rabbi Yochanan, Rav and Rabbi Yochanan debate. חד אמר אם רצו לזמן
מזמנין, chad amar im ratzu lezamen mezamnin, they can if they want.
וחד אמר אם רצו לזמן מזמנין, ve-chad amar im ratzu lezamen mezamnin,
they can. תנן, tnan, let's take a look if we can prove
it. שלשה שאכלו כאחת חייבים לזמן, shlosha she-achlu ke-achat chayavim lezamen, three
who ate have to do a זימון. zimmun. שלשה אין שנים לא,
shlosha in shnayim lo, three yes but not two. So the answer
is obvious. התם חובה, hatam chova, no, there it means they are
obligated. הכא רשות, hacha reshut, here we're trying to argue that it
could be a permission to do it as a זימון zimmun of
two. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, שלשה שאכלו כאחת חייבים
לזמן. shlosha she-achlu ke-achat chayavim lezamen.
Another, another I believe it's a ברייתא braita says to match the
משנה mishnah we have and they cannot divide. And they cannot divide.
So they cannot say, one person can't say I'm doing my own
זימון. zimmun, They're not allowed to split up. You have to do
a זימון zimmun. together. Not doing my own, I'm doing my own
בענטשינג. bentshing. You're not, not you're not allowed to split up. So
שלשה אין שנים לא, shlosha in shnayim lo, three yes only not
two. Now again why can't it say the same answer? Here you're
obligated. So רש"י Rashi says no, because if two were an option
then one person could say I'm leaving, you guys can still do
a זימון, zimmun, you have the option, why do you need me?
I'm leaving. תוספות Tosafot says yeah but that wouldn't explain why the
one guy is allowed to leave because he's getting out of the
זימון. zimmun. He might not be, you know, hurting them but he's
hurting himself. So anyway תוספות Tosafot says there's, the end of it
says, the end of this says that even four people can't split
up as two and two. So he said that certainly proves the
point because if you were able to, if two you're able to
do a זימון, zimmun. what's the big deal? Four split up as
two and two and each one does a זימון. zimmun So the
גמרא Gemara says שאני התם דקבלו להו בחובה מעיקרא. shani hatam de-kabelu
lehu be-chova me-ikara. No there, once you started as three you had
an obligation to do a זימון. zimmun So you don't want to
change doing a זימון zimmun, qua obligation as doing a זימון zimmun,
qua רשות. reshut. It's true you'll do a זימון, zimmun. but it's
different when you're doing it as a רשות reshut and as an
obligation. רש"י Rashi quotes the famous line, you know, that better is
מצווה ועושה ממי שאינו מצווה ועושה. metzuveh ve-oseh mi-mi she-eino metzuveh ve-oseh.
So if you're in a state of the able to do it
as an obligation, you don't lower that performance and do it as
an optional performance. Okay so but two could still be an option.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, השמש שהיה משמש על השנים,
ha-shamash she-haya meshamesh al ha-shnayim, so the the attendant, the the servant
that was, you know, being a waiter for two other people. הרי
זה אוכל עמהם, harei ze ochel imahem, he's allowed to eat with
them. Meaning this is not a question of זימון, zimmun, well it's
a it's a direct, it's an indirect effect of זימון. zimmun. Since
if he eats with them he'll help them make a זימון, zimmun,
then we assume implicitly that they have, the people in the meal
have given him permission to have some of the food because they'll
want him to be able to be part of the זימון. zimmun
So he doesn't have to ask permission to eat the food, it's
assumed that he it's okay that he has some of the food.
אף על פי שלא נתנו לו רשות, af al pi she-lo natnu
lo reshut, even if they didn't give him explicit permission. היה משמש
על השלשה, haya meshamesh al ha-shlosha, if he was attending to three,
הרי זה אינו אוכל עמהם, harei ze eino ochel imahem, they don't
need him for their זימון, zimmun הרי זה אינו אוכל עמהם, harei
ze eino ochel imahem, he doesn't eat with them, אלא אם כן
נתנו לו רשות ela im ken natnu lo reshut unless they explicitly
gave him permission. So so you see there why would they have
implicitly given him permission if they could do it even with two?
So the גמרא Gemara says שאני התם, shani hatam, again there it's
different. דניחא להו דניקבעו בחובה, de-nicha lehu de-nikbe'u be-chova, even though they'd
rather do it as three, they'd rather do it as an obligation
rather than as a permission. Again the sense of doing things as
obligations gives it greater weight than doing it as just okay you
can if you want to, it doesn't really count or whatever it's
not the same big deal. So therefore they'd want him to eat
so that they can become obligatory, but two still might be a
permission. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, נשים מזמנות לעצמן ועבדים
מזמנים לעצמם. nashim mezamnot le-atzman ve-avadim mezamnim le-atzman. So women make a
זימון zimmun by themselves. This wasn't our משנה. mishnah. Our משנה mishnah
says men don't make it with women, but this is in ערכין,
Erchin, we quote the ברייתא braita that women can make a זימון
zimmun by themselves and slaves can make a זימון zimmun. by themselves.
נשים ועבדים וקטנים אם רצו לזמן אין מזמנין. nashim ve-avadim ve-ktanim im
ratzu lezamen ein mezamnin. But if slaves, women, and children want to
do it together they can't do it as a group. So let's
get, I'll get back to discussing the whys of this in a
minute but let's see how the גמרא Gemara is using this, using
this. So the גמרא Gemara says It says והא מאה נשי כתרי
גברי דמיין, v'ha me'ah nashi k'trei gavrei damyan, very sort of provocative
line. It says a hundred women is considered like two men. What
does that mean? It means that even a hundred women are not
obligated. It's a רשות, reshut, right? It says נשים ועבדים מזמנות לעצמן,
Nashim va'avadim mezamnot l'atzman, the way the גמרא Gemara I'll read this
רש"י's Rashi way then I'll discuss תוספות's Tosafot way. רש"י's Rashi way
is: look, we're assuming that women are not obligated, but it says
מזמנות לעצמן, mezamnot l'atzman, it says that they're a רשות, reshut, okay?
So you see that that women are considered like the two-men category,
not an obligation but yes a רשות. reshut. So even if you
have three women, however many women you have, it's in this category
parallel to the two men where it's not an obligation and it's
a רשות. reshut. ותני נשים מזמנות לעצמן, v'tani nashim mezamnot l'atzman, we
see that there is an idea of doing זימון zimmun even though
it's not obligatory like the case by women. ועבדים מזמנים לעצמם. v'avadim
mezamnim l'atzmam. The גמרא Gemara. says לא, שאני התם דאיכא דעות. lo,
shani hatam d'ika de'ot. There it's different. There, although it is it
might not be obligatory, again this is רש"י's Rashi way I'll tell
you תוספות's Tosafot way in a bit. I know, I'm reading it
רש"י's Rashi way first, okay? I'm going to give you the other
explanation in a minute. But you still have three. Remember the פסוק
we learned it from was הבו לה' איתי ונרוממה שמו יחדיו, havu
l'Adonai iti v'neromemah shemo yachdav, גדלו לה' איתי ונרוממה שמו יחדיו. gadlu
l'Adonai iti v'neromemah shemo yachdav. That so there even if it's not
obligatory still a having a group of three of multiple voices is
still gives it greater weight. And therefore we can assume that you
can have a case where it's a רשות reshut and not a
חיוב chiyuv if it's three. But with two where you don't even
have the one person calling to two others, two, that maybe is
not even a permission, that is completely not this institution. That's the
way רש"י Rashi reads this גמרא. Gemara Now תוספות Tosafot, disagree. תוספות
Tosafot says the והא מאה נשי כתרי גברי דמיין v'ha me'ah nashi
k'trei gavrei damyan doesn't mean in this case the hundred count as
two meaning that there's no sense of obligation. תוספות Tosafot. says it
means that normally women don't count, you know, for things that men
count for like a מנין minyan and so on. So the assumption
is if normally women don't count to create an obligatory group, here
too they also should not. And if you read it that way,
that was the הוה אמינא hava amina but the answer of איכא
דעות ika de'ot could be coming to reject that and could be
coming to say that this is different. This is not something like
a מנין or something else where normally we assume you need, you
know, it's men and not women. Here it's about a group of
people and even women could be just as obligated as men, or
at least you know, it's a רשות reshut but maybe even more
meaning equally obligated. Reading it very different than רש"י Rashi that the
הוה אמינא hava amina was that they had a different status but
the מסקנא maskana could be that they have the same status. If
you take a look at let's look at תוספות, Tosafot two quick
תוספות Tosafot I want to show you. First והא מאה נשי כתרי
גברי דמיין. v'ha me'ah nashi k'trei gavrei damyan. He says לעניין קיבוץ
תפילה, l'inyan kibbutz tfillah, לעניין כל דבר שבקדושה, l'inyan kol davar she'bikdushah,
meaning in normal things when you need a מנין we assume that
it's men and not women. And then the answer here שאני התם
דאיכא דעות. shani hatam d'ika de'ot. Next תוספות. Tosafot מכאן משמע דנשים
יכולות לזמן לעצמן. mikan mashma d'nashim yacholot l'zamen l'atzman. First he says
יכולות. yacholot. Hold on. וכן עשו בנות רבנו אברהם חמיו של רבנו
יהודה, v'chen asu bnot Rabbeinu Avraham chamiv shel Rabbeinu Yehudah, the daughters
of רבנו אברהם Rabbeinu Avraham did this, not the daughters of רש"י
Rashi we're always hearing about the daughters of רש"י. Rashi. Anyway, על
פי אביהן, al pi avihen, by their father's instruction. But he says
ומיהו לא נהגו העולם כן. umihu lo nahagu ha'olam ken. תוספות Tosfos
says it's not the מנהג for women to do זימון. zimmun. וקשה,
v'kashyeh, so that's if it's just a רשות. reshut. If it's just
a רשות reshut you could say לא נהגו. lo nahagu. But then
תוספות says אמאי לא נהגו? amai lo nahagu? מדיתני מזמנות mideitani mezamnot
משמע דקאמר דחייבות לזמן. mashma d'ka'amar d'chayavot l'zamen. Okay? And then he
goes on and discusses whether women have a חיוב chiyuv to do
זימון zimmun or only a רשות reshut to do זימון. zimmun And
there's a major מחלוקת ראשונים machloket rishonim whether women have a חיוב
chiyuv to do זימון zimmun and many understand that they do. That
נשים מזמנות nashim mezamnot means the מסקנא maskana of the גמרא Gemara
is that not that it's רשות, reshut, that it actually is a
חיוב chiyuv and that the הגהות אשרי Hagahot Ashri felt it was
חיוב chiyuv and so on. That is a major debate of ראשונים.
rishonim. The other question which which we have which I'll just mention
now but we certainly don't have the time to get into is
why if women do have a חיוב, chiyuv, you know, and and
women anyway are חייב בברכת המזון, chayav b'birkat hamazon although there was
an earlier גמרא Gemara that questioned maybe it was דאורייתא de'oraita maybe
it was דרבנן. derabbanan. But if we assume women are חייב בברכת
המזון דאורייתא chayav b'birkat hamazon de'oraita which is the assumption, why should
they not be why should they not be חייב chayav in a
זימון zimmun. and why should they not be able to do it
with men? So if they're and certainly the question is strengthened if
they're חייב chayav בברכת המזון birkat hamazon, and חייב chayav in a
זימון zimmun. then why can't they do it with men? And here
the גמרא later will say that there's a concern about a sense
of like פריצותא pritzuta that men and women together as a group,
women and slaves and and together as a group, you know, there's
questions about is it is it, you know, in in societies which
are very segregated, this would be seen as an unseemly type of
a grouping which then opens up questions about how might that change
nowadays? Okay? And there is recently, you know, been published some articles
about that, even that came out of the גוש Gush around this
question about nowadays certainly in a family context could these issues be
different about making these mixed groups? But that's a separate question. One
question is as separate groups are women obligated and according to תוספות
possible the answer is yes, even obligated.
So it's acceptable, it's not a problem for women to be with
male slaves. That's okay.
No, it is a problem. That's why women and slaves can also
not be the group. Women by themselves, slaves by the groups, not
as a group. Yes.
I noticed that it says
נשים ועבדים
וקטנים.
Nashim ve-Avadim
ve-Ketanim.
Alright, so that... I'm not yet not going to get into that
now. Okay. So let's take a look at the הגמרא Gemara continues.
אי הכי אימא סיפא. Ei hachi eima seifa. Let's look at the
end of it. נשים ועבדים אם רצו לזמן אין מזמנין. Nashim ve-avadim
im ratzu lezamen ein mezamnin. Oh so I actually I
actually jumped ahead of the הגמרא. Gemara. So then if that's true
that women maybe are even obligated, certainly רשות, reshus, why can't women
do it together with slaves? אמאי לא והא איכא דעות? Amai lo
ve-ha ika de'os? You have multiple people, let's do a
זימון. zimmun. שאני התם משום פריצותא. Shani hasam mishum pritzusa. No, they
always considered it to be sort of, you know, breaking boundaries and
it would lead to sexual impropriety and so on. Okay. So now,
so anyway, so we haven't proved it yet. Yes, it's possible the
way רש"י Rashi reads you have the example of רשות reshus by
women, but that's not... that's at least three. According to תוספות the
conclusion might be women are obligated. So the הגמרא Gemara says תסתיים
דרב דאמר אם רצו לזמן אין מזמנין. Tistayem de-Rav d-amar im ratzu
lezamen ein mezamnin. Let's try to prove that רב Rav: is the
one. We didn't know which one said which. That רב Rav is
the one that says that if they want to they're not able
to. דאמר רב דימי בר יוסף אמר רב. D-amar Rav Dimi bar
Yosef amar Rav. רב דימי בר יוסף Rav Dimi bar Yosef said
in the name of רב: Rav שלושה שאכלו כאחד ויצא אחד מהם
לשוק. Shlosha she-achlu ke-echad ve-yatza echad me-hem la-shuk. Three that ate together
and one had to... went out to the marketplace. And there he
is out in the market and you... now you want to bench.
קורין לו ומזמנין עליו. Korin lo u-mezamnin alav. You call to him
and you make him part of the זימון. zimmun. It means he
doesn't have to come back to sit at the table. He like
turns around and faces you. He hears you, he answers you, but
he's still out there in the middle of the street. So טעמא
דקורין לו. Ta'ama de-korin lo. So this is only good because you
call to him. הא לא קורין לו לא. Ha lo korin lo
lo. If you don't call to him, no, then you couldn't do
a זימון. zimmun. So you see two is not good. So the
הגמרא Gemara has the standard answer to that.
שאני התם דאיתחילו להו בחובה מעיקרא. Shani hasam de-itchilu le-hu be-chova me-ikara.
No, there you started with three. Once you started with an obligatory
three, then you want to... you want to have that three at
the end. You don't want to shift from obligation to
רשות. reshus. Okay. So the הגמרא Gemara says let's try the other
way. אלא תסתיים דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר אם רצו לזמן אין מזמנין.
Ela tistayem de-Rabbi Yochanan hu d-amar im ratzu lezamen ein mezamnin. Maybe
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the one that says that two cannot
do it.
דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן שנים שאכלו כאחד אחד
מהם יוצא בברכת חבירו. D-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
shnayim she-achlu ke-echad echad me-hem yotzei be-virchas chaveiro. So here we get
this question about שומע כעונה shomei'a ke-oneh as opposed to the institution
of זימון. zimmun? If two people ate together one can be יוצא
yotzei with somebody else.
והוינא בה מאי קמשמע לן? Ve-havina bah mai kamashma lan? What's that
teaching us? תנינא. Tnina. We taught a general principle. שמע ולא ענה
יצא. Shama ve-lo ana yatza. If somebody hears somebody else's ברכה bracha
even if you don't say אמן, יצא, yatza, you're יוצא. yotzei. So
of course you can be יוצא yotzei with somebody else's ברכה. bracha.
דאמר רבי זירא לומר שאין ברכת הזימון ביניהם. D-amar Rabbi Zeira lomar
she-ein birchas ha-zimmun beineihem. No, the point of saying two, that it's
שומע כעונה, shomei'a ke-oneh, is to tell us שאין ברכת הזימון ביניהם.
she-ein birchas ha-zimmun beineihem.
They might be יוצא yotzei through the piggybacking of שומע כעונה—you shomei'a
ke-oneh make a ברכה bracha and I listen—but they're not יוצא yotzei
through the institution of זימון. zimmun. It's only... what? ברכת המזון.
Birchas ha-Mazon. ברכת הזימון ביניהם.
Birchas ha-zimmun beineihem. Oh really, of זימון?
zimmun I'm מזון. mazun. Yeah, I'm מזון. mazun. That's how it's...
ברכת
הזימון.
Birchas
ha-zimmun.
Okay. Anyway, so תסתיים. tistayem. That is a good proof. Now this
is critical because this says it is possible to be יוצא שומע
כעונה. yotzei shomei'a ke-oneh. But it's a very different type of a
phenomenon. It is not the phenomenon of זימון. zimmun So if you're
two you can be יוצא שומע כעונה yotzei shomei'a ke-oneh but it
is not זימון zimmun and we're going to see later in the
הגמרא, Gemara, not today, that that clearly is non-desirable. So when we
said the נידח הסבה nidach haseiba in the beginning, of זימון zimmun.
at the end, that you're not supposed to piggyback on somebody, בדיעבד
be-di'avad you can. You can do שומע כעונה shomei'a ke-oneh for these
types of things. But it is not ideal for these types of
ברכות הנהנין. brachos ha-nehenin. You should not piggyback on somebody else. You
should do it yourself or you should do it as part of
a זימון as part of a group. And just to end this
the
הגמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנן לרב הונא. Amar
lei Rava bar Rav Chanan le-Rav Huna. So he said to רב
הונא: Rav Huna: והרבנן דאתו ממערבא אמרי. Ve-ha-rabbanan d-asu mi-ma'arava amri. But
the רבנן rabbanan who came from מערבא ma'arava said: אם רצו לזמן
מזמנין. Im ratzu lezamen mezamnin. If they want to you can, which
sounds like מאי לאו דשמיע להו מרבי יוחנן? mai lav de-shami'a le-hu
mi-Rabbi Yochanan? And since they're coming from מערבא ma'arava presumably they heard
it from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan say two are not allowed? The רבנן rabbanan from מערבא ma'arava
say two are allowed.
לא דשמיע להו מרב מקמי דנחית לבבל. Lo de-shami'a le-hu mi-Rav mikamei
de-nachis le-Bavel. They heard it from רב Rav before רב made ירידה.
yeridah. So it could be that רב is the one that says
two is allowed, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the one that says
two is not allowed. We will see tomorrow on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah that we rule like רבי יוחנן—two Rabbi Yochanan is not an
option. You need a minimum of three. You can have no less
than three for a זימון. Okay.